Guide to the Wyatt T. Dixon Papers, 1850s-1987
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wyatt T. Dixon papers 1850s-1987
Dixon, Wyatt T.
3.6 linear feet Extent: 2700 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
RL.00313
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research/restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Wyatt T. Dixon Papers were donated to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1981 and 1986.
Biographical Note
1894, Oct. 27 Born, Durham, N.C.
1917, July 25 Called into service for the United States Army, 30th Division, 113th Field Artillery, Battery C, Durham, N.C. Dixon made Company Clerk.
1917, Sept. 16 113th Field Artillery, Battery C, moved to Camp Sevier, S.C.
1918, May 19 113th Field Artillery, Battery C, moved to Camp Mills, Long Island, N.Y.
1918, May 27 113th Field Artillery, Battery C, departed for France on the [Armagh ?]
1918, June 7 113th Field Artillery, Battery C, landed in Liverpool, England; departed England on the Prince George
1918, June 13 113th Field Artillery, Battery C, arrived in La Havre, France
1918, Sept. 12 113th Field Artillery, Battery C, participated in the St. Michiel offensive
1918, Sept. 26 113th Field Artillery, Battery C, participated in the Meuse-Argonne campaign
1919, Jan. 14 113th Field Artillery, Battery C turned in their horses and supplies
1919, March 19 113th Field Artillery, Battery C, returned to United States, landed at Newport News, Va.
1919, June 1-1962 Writer and photographer for the Durham Morning Herald and The Durham Sun newspapers, Durham Herald Co., Durham, N.C.
1933-1986 Wrote weekly columns, Along the Battlefront about World War I and How Times Do Change about Durham, N.C., for The Durham Sun
1962 Retired from The Durham Sun, but continued to write "How Times Do Change" until 1986
1986, Jan. 1 Died, Durham, N.C.
Collection Overview
The Wyatt T. Dixon Papers span the 1850s to 1987, although the bulk of the material dates from 1918 to the 1960s. The collection consists of diaries, photographs, photomechanical prints, postcards, clippings, correspondence, speeches, scrapbooks, printed materials, forms, military records, leaflets, and maps. The Pictures Series comprises the largest portion of the collection. The collection documents the activities of the United States Army, American Expeditionary Forces, 30th Division, 113th Field Artillery Unit, Battery C, from 1917 to 1919; Durham, North Carolina; and Dixon's career as a journalist.
The World War I Series chronicles the activities of the American Expeditionary Forces, 113th Field Artillery Unit, Battery C, which consisted primarily of men from Durham, N.C. Dixon's diaries chronicle the unit's movements and activities in the United States and Europe including England, France, Belgium, and Luxembourg. Battery C was involved in the Saint Michiel offensive and the Meuse-Argonne Campaign. The diaries describe camp life in the United States and Europe, including daily routines; camp conditions; outbreaks of measles and other medical situations; and the soldiers' personal recreational activities. The journey by ship to Europe is also described in detail, including the sale of food to the soldiers and the conditions on board. Civilian responses to the soldiers as they visited or traveled through towns and cities in America, France, Belgium, and Luxembourg are noted throughout the diaries. Dixon mentions a unit of African-American soldiers was at Mont Dore, France. There are some snapshot photographs of Battery C which Dixon probably created with his Kodak camera and some formal panoramic photographs of the entire unit. Letters written by Dixon and his family while he was in the Army are in the Writings Series.
The Writings Series contains some personal correspondence and a diary, but the bulk of the series documents Dixon's career as a writer for newspapers published by the Durham Herald Company in Durham, N.C. In his column How Times Do Change, Dixon described life in Durham and the surrounding area and the manner in which cityscapes and social life had changed over the past decades. The bulk of the pictures in the Pictures Series document Durham, N.C., and appear to have been collected by Dixon to illustrate his articles.
The Pictures Series consists primarily of photographs and documents social life and cityscapes in Durham, N.C. Pictures include buildings such as banks, businesses, cemeteries, churches, court houses, dams and power plants, hospitals, hotels and inns, plantations (abandoned), post offices, schools, and tobacco warehouses and factories. There are street scenes and aerial views. Pictures of people include portraits and candid scenes of groups engaged in social activities. There are pictures of events such as holiday celebrations and parades. Transportation, including trolleys, buses, fire fighting equipment and train depots, is documented.
The Durham Printed Materials Series and the Miscellaneous Series include information about the City of Durham and Durham County, genealogical information about Dixon's family, and the minutes book of a social club for young men.
Subject Headings
Dixon, Wyatt T.; Soldiers -- Diaries; Soldiers' writings, American; World War, 1914-1918 -- Veterans; Veterans -- North Carolina; United States. Army. 113th Field Artillery, 1917-1919. Battery C.; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces; United States. Army. Field Artillery, 113th. Battery C.; Durham (N.C.); Durham (N.C.) -- History; Photographs -- Durham (N.C.); Cityscapes; Postcards; Diaries; Durham County (N.C.)
Contents of Collection
- Writings Series, 1915-1987, undated (bulk 1930s-1980s).
  Includes correspondence, a diary/autograph book, clippings, a scrapbook, printed material, notes, and manuscripts. The first part of the series contains personal correspondence and miscellaneous publications. The "How Times Do Change" Subseries contains copies of Dixon's articles by that title and drafts and notes for articles, as well as a volume of reproductions of the articles. The subseries is arranged with the published volume first, followed by miscellaneous articles in chronological order, and finally drafts and notes for articles arrranged by subject.
  - Correspondence, 1918-1985, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Diary/Notebook, 1915, Oct.-1917, Feb. (Box 1)
  - Mangum, Willie P.: Biographical sketch, undated (Box 1)
  - Municipal Progress Under Manager Government II. Durham Gets More and Better Service. In National Municipal Review, 14(8), 1925 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper articles, 1935, Aug.-1952, Apr. (Box 1)
  - Clippings scrapbook (re: Durham, N.C.), 1920s-1930s, undated (Box 1)
  - How Times Do Change Subseries (Box 1)
    - Published volume (article reprints), 1987 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper articles, 1933, Sept.-1983, Mar., undated (Box 2)
    - Drafts and notes for newspaper articles: (Box 2)
      - Buildings, 1942-1982, undated (Box 2)
      - Churches, 1949, undated (Box 2)
      - Fire department and fires, 1974-1980, undated (Box 2)
      - Government, city positions, directories, Durham overviews, 1946, undated (Box 2)
      - Hotels, 1983, undated (Box 2)
      - Military, 1934-1945, undated (Box 2)
      - Newspapers, 1933, undated (Box 2)
      - People, 1933-1978, undated (Box 2)
      - Streets, transportation, utilities, 1963-1984, undated (Box 2)
      - Theaters, undated (Box 2)
      - Tobacco, undated (Box 2)
      - Trinity College/Duke University, 1962-1980, undated (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1936-1984, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- World War I Series, 1917-1980, undated (bulk 1917-1919). (Box 2)
  Includes diaries, manuscripts, letters, printed material, a service record, photographs, negatives, a passenger list, and clippings. See also oversize. Arranged with the diaries first, followed by a history of the unit, records from reunions, and pictures at the end.
  - Diary fragment, 1917, July? (Box 3)
  - Diary, 1917, Aug. 30-1918, July 14, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Diary, 1918, Mar. 9-1919, Mar. 20, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Diary transcription, 1917, Sept. 16-1919, Mar. 21 (Box 3)
  - History of 113th Field Artillery, Battery C, ca. 1918 (Box 3)
  - Printed material, ca. 1917 (Box 3)
  - Record Books: insurance, memos, and correspondence, 1918 (Box 3)
  - Reunions, 113th Field Artillery Unit, Battery C, 1969-1980, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Service record: Sims, Willie H., 1917 (Box 4)
  - Pictures: World War I: 113th Field Artillery, 1918, undated (Box 4)
  - Negatives: World War I: 113th Field Artillery, ca. 1918 (Box 4)
- Durham: Printed Materials Series, 1873-1981, n.d (Box 4)
  Includes primarily printed material including advertisements, brochures, leaflets, directories, clippings, reports and house organs. See also oversize.
  - Businesses, 1884-1961, undated (Box 4)
  - Camp Butner, 1971, undated; Brooklyn Tabernacle Sunday School, 1892 (Box 4)
  - City and county public Works, government and public services, 1873-1925, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Herald-Sun house organs, 1944-1975, undated (Box 4)
  - Maps: City of Durham, 1881-1981; Durham County, undated (Box 4)
  - Organizations/Social clubs, 1913-1974 (Box 4)
  - Promotional, 1913-1981, undated (Box 4)
  - Schools, 1881-1926 (Box 4)
  - Trinity College, 1889, undated (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1863-1986. (Box 4)
  Includes correspondence, clippings, notes, a sermon, lists, treasury forms, a social club's minutes record book, poems, leaflets, and speeches.
  - Miscellaneous: 1863-1980, undated (Box 5)
  - Biographical and genealogical information, 1936-1986, n.d (Box 5)
  - Communist Party in North Carolina, 1950, July-ca. 1952 (Box 5)
  - Durham city and county, 1869-1974 (Box 5)
  - Speeches, 1963, undated (Box 5)
  - Top-Notch Club: Minute Book, 1913, Feb. 25-1914, May 7 (Box 5)
  - Clippings: By authors other than Dixon or unsigned, 1924, Jan.-1986, Jan. (Box 5)
- Pictures Series, 1850s(?)-1976, undated (bulk 1920s-1960s, undated) (Box 5)
  Includes photographs, copy prints, photomechanical prints, negatives, and postcards. See also oversize. Arranged by subject: People: Identified, arranged alphabetically by surname of principle individual in the photograph, and then People: Unidentified; followed by Groups: Identified, arranged alphabetically, and then Groups: Unidentified; Places: Identified, arranged alphabetically, and then Places: Unidentified; Miscellaneous; Postcards, arranged by location; and Negatives.
  - People: (Box 5)
    - Identified: A-W, 1890s-1970s, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - Unidentified, 1953, undated (Box 6)
  - Groups: (Box 6)
    - Identified: (Box 6)
      - County and city officials, governors, judges, mayors, 1922-1953, n.d (Box 6)
      - Dixon, Wyatt T. with others, 1976, undated (Box 6)
      - Durham Morning Herald staff, 1920, undated (Box 6)
      - Empty Stocking Club, 1927-1952, undated (Box 6)
      - Firemen, policemen, and street car operators, music groups, ca. 1885-1900, undated (Box 6)
      - Military and veterans, 1921-1971, undated (Box 6)
      - Schools and orphanages, 1895-1926, undated (Box 6)
      - Spanish-American war soldiers in camps in Kentucky and Georgia, 1898 (Box 6)
      - Trinity College and Duke University, 1925, undated (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous, 1911-1953, undated (Box 6)
    - Unidentified, 1957, undated (Box 6)
  - Places: (Box 6)
    - Aerial views of Durham, 1938-1960, undated (Box 6)
    - Banks, 1878-1973, undated (Box 7)
    - Bennett Place, 1964, undated (Box 7)
    - Buildings (miscellaneous): (Box 7)
      - Identified: 1882-1969, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 7)
    - Businesses (various): (Box 7)
      - General, undated (Box 7)
      - Interiors, 1904, undated (Box 7)
    - Camp Butner, 1945, undated (Box 7)
    - Cemeteries and burials, 1934-1954, undated (Box 7)
    - Chapel Hill and Hillsborough, 1930, undated (Box 7)
    - Churches, ca. 1850(?)-1976, undated (Box 7)
    - Courthouses, ca. 1887(?)-1963, undated (Box 7)
    - Dams, power plants, 1899-1925, n.d (Box 7)
    - Ft. Macon, 1935, undated (Box 7)
    - Homes: Identified, 1883-1965, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Hospitals, ca. 1976(?), undated (Box 8)
    - Hotels and inns, 1891-1975, undated (Box 8)
    - Plantations: Fairntosh, undated, Stagville, undated (Box 8)
    - Post offices, ca. 1906(?)-1961, undated (Box 8)
    - Schools, 1882-1992, undated (Box 8)
    - Streets: (Box 8)
      - Identified, 1895-1976, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
      - Unidentified, 1927-1963, undated (Box 8)
    - Tobacco warehouses, factories, barns, and stores, ca. 1870-1970, undated (Box 8)
    - Trinity College, ca. 1892(?)-1960, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Trinity Methodist Church, 1860-1923 (Box 8)
    - YMCA, 1956, undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous: (Box 8)
    - Christmas/holiday, 1937-1967, undated (Box 8)
    - Hurricane Hazel, 1956 (Box 8)
    - Parades, including military, 1895-1945, undated (Box 8)
    - Transportation, including depots and fire fighting equipment, ca. 1888- ca. 1968(?), undated (Box 9)
    - Cook tent at Div. Hospital, Lexington, Ky., undated (Box 9)
  - Postcards: (Box 9)
    - Durham, N.C., 1907-1967, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Chapel Hill and Hillsborough, N.C., undated (Box 9)
    - Europe, undated (Box 9)
  - Negatives: (Box 9)
    - People: (Box 9)
      - Identified: C-D, M, undated (Box 9)
      - Groups: (Box 9)
        - Identified, undated (Box 9)
        - Unidentified, undated (Box 9)
      - Military and veterans, undated (Box 9)
    - Places: (Box 9)
      - Banks, undated (Box 9)
      - Buildings: Identified: schools, library, bank, Masonic Temple, unidentified, undated (Box 9)
      - Businesses (various), undated (Box 9)
      - Churches, 1878, undated (Box 9)
      - Homes identified, undated (Box 9)
      - Hospitals, hotels, and inns, 1961, undated (Box 9)
      - Plantations: Fairntosh, undated, Stagville, undated (Box 9)
      - Tobacco warehouses and stores, undated (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous: Transportation, undated (Box 9)
    - Postcards: Durham, undated (Box 9)
- Oversize Materials (Box 9)
  - World War I Series (Box 9)
    - Pictures: (Box 10)
      - 113th Field Artillery Unit, Batteries A-E, Headquarters Co., Supply Co., Officers, Field Artillery Unit, 1919, March 20 (Box 10)
      - 113th Field Artillery Unit, Battery C, Camp Sevier, S.C., 1918, Feb. (Box 10)
      - Unidentified soldiers, undated (Opaperfolder 1, Box 10)
    - 113th Field Artillery Unit, Battery C, passenger list for returning members, 1919, Feb. 28 (Opaperfolder Folder 1, Box 10)
  - Durham Printed Material Series (Box 10)
    - City and county public works, government and public services, 1911; Promotional, 1905 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Series (Box 10)
    - Maps: City of Durham, 1891; Durham property owned by B. L. Duke, 1901; railway routes in Va. and N.C., undated (Opaperfolder Folder 1, Box 10)
  - Pictures Series (Box 10)
    - People: (Box 10)
      - Identified: Government officials, 1948-; Durham Sun staff, n.d (Box 10)
      - Groups: (Box 10)
        - Identified, 1885, 1916, undated; unidentified, undated (Box 10)
    - Places: (Box 10)
      - Buildings: Identified, undated; unidentified, undated (Box 10)
      - Streets unidentified, ca. 1930-1961 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous: Parades, military, undated (Box 10)